[Music]
so today I've had to try and find the
most sheltered place out here because
it's really really windy but today we're
going to talk about carrageenan it's a
natural food additive that's commonly
used in the food industry it will
explore the different types of
carrageenan and what they used for which
one to use in ice cream and
predominantly what it does when you use
it so stick around and we'll talk about
another stabilizer
[Music]
carrageenan is derived from red seaweed
which is harvested from the coast of
various countries including Indonesia
Philippines and Chile
the seaweed is processed to extract the
carrageenan by means of a hot Alkali
solution so it's heated up to around 100
degrees C that allows the carrigine in
itself to be extracted from the seaweed
there are three main types of
carrageenan Kappa Iota and Lambda now
Kappa carrageenan forms a strong rigid
gel and is used in a production of
various dairy products such as ice cream
Iota carrageenan forms a soft flexible
gel and is commonly used in the
production of jellies and puddings
and then there's Lambda carrageenan that
doesn't form a gel and is used as a
thickener and stabilizer but it is used
in high fat ice creams that you don't
need gelling Factor the Kappa or Iota
versions
gels and ice creams are something you
may or may not want usually a
synergistic gel is desired in low-fat
ice creams and not so much in ice cream
with medium to high fat levels
they can create slimy mouthfeels if you
use them with ice creams with too high
fat think of a gel as a way to mimic the
mouth feel of high fat ice creams
there are a few resources online that
will show you how stabilizers work
together to create gels I've put a few
links in the description below to such
sites such as dream Scoops and
underbelly
but now let's talk about carrageenan and
if it's good for you
now watch cargaining is generally
considered safe some Studies have
suggested that it makes may cause
inflammation in the digestive tract for
some people just to put that into
perspective red meat refined grains such
as white rice soda fried foods anything
with sugar in it is also a going to
create inflammation in your digestive
tract so it's not unique in that respect
as with any food additive it's important
to use carrageenan in moderation and
just pay attention to your body's
reaction
if you want to try using carrigin in
your ice cream
start with small amounts as with all
stabilizers always start with 0.1
percent because you can always gradually
increase as needed
so carrageenan
it will stabilize your ice cream base it
will control free water along with guar
gum if you combine it with that and if
you combine it with locust bean gum then
it will reduce your Ice Crystal size as
well so that's why you'll generally find
carrageenan is used alongside another
stabilizer and that
Locus bean gum combo has been used for
years you can tweak it depending on the
result and your ice cream that you're
making
but as you can see all these stabilizers
can be worked and used together to
reduce Ice Crystal size to make a
thicker more viscous base which in turn
will give you a creamier mouth feel
and actually allows you to reduce fat on
your ice cream as well
if you're making a low-fat ice cream you
would want a gel to be created and that
is to mimic the fat content that is to
take control of that free water within
your recipe so you don't get large ice
crystals when it freezes
if you're making a high fat or medium
fat ice cream so anything from around 10
to 12 and upwards of fat content you
wouldn't want a gel to be created
because you're going to get a slimy
texture and when you scoop it it's going
to be really really strange
gelato recipes are by Nature all lower
fat so they're created with usually
around eight percent fat or less there
are now gelatos that go up to 12 and the
the line between gelato and ice cream is
being blurred and that's because people
think gelato is something very unique
and it's not it's it's just a different
form of ice cream it's a lower fat high
sugar form of ice cream so that's why
within gelato recipes you can use more
stabilizers because you've got a lot
more free water a lot less fat and
that's why that synergistic action of
different types of stabilizers combined
will make your gelato stand out a lot of
people make gelato and expect it to be
as creamy and smooth as ice cream but
they don't add anywhere near as much
stabilizer or any stabilizer and in
reality all you're going to get is an
icy block when you put it in a freezer
what you want is to use the right amount
stabilizer for the recipe that you're
making if you're unsure you can contact
me either through YouTube on any video
in the comment section I will reply or
you can go over to my website we'll put
a link on the screen here and you can
send me an email and ask me any
questions you like if you want immediate
response to any questions that you have
you can join YouTube membership for the
channel and I put some links in the
description you can also just click the
button up here and it will take you and
if you are a member of the channel
you'll get immediate response and I will
keep helping you until we've got it
right and there we go that's another
simplified ice cream stabilizer video
for carrageenans there's obviously a lot
more information for all of these I will
do a larger video stabilizers part two
when we're actually in the new house so
hold fast for that one but for now
thanks very much for watching don't
forget to like And subscribe and I'll
see you next time
thank you
foreign